<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Curiously Recurring Thoughts in Programming</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Curiously Recurring Thoughts in Programming</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-gb</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:35:34 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://osadalakmal.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Avoiding burnout in software domain</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/avoiding-burnout-in-software-domain/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:35:34 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/avoiding-burnout-in-software-domain/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/avoiding-burnout-in-software-domain/young-woman-eyes-closed-hand-on-forehead-768.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Avoiding burnout in software domain" /&gt;How to avoid the dangers of the trade
  What is burnout? Why does it happen? It won&amp;rsquo;t happen to me How to avoid it  Prioritize self-care Shift your perspective Reduce exposure to job stressors Seek out connections   Mental health and software industry    What is burnout?   You know the drill. It starts with a couple spillovers from your usual sprints. It snowballs in to a stream of issues and before you know it, you are at risk of missing a major deadline.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Agile : The Snake Oil for Cobra Bites</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/agile-the-snake-oil-for-cobra-bites/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 21:57:42 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/agile-the-snake-oil-for-cobra-bites/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/agile-the-snake-oil-for-cobra-bites/agile-poster.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Agile : The Snake Oil for Cobra Bites" /&gt;How the rebellion got subverted
  The agile manifesto - The Rebellion that was not The call is coming from inside the house Return to roots Why is it so easy to fail? How to undo this? Understanding the what, why and how Cutting out the fluff Understand but do not measure Use the tools provided in whatever flavour of Agile you chose To be continued    The agile manifesto - The Rebellion that was not</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Hyperscan C&#43;&#43; Wrapper</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/hyperscan-cpp-wrapper/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 22:16:45 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/hyperscan-cpp-wrapper/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/hyperscan-cpp-wrapper/Hyperspace_falcon.webp" alt="Featured image of post Hyperscan C&#43;&#43; Wrapper" /&gt;(or why using the phrase &amp;ldquo;C/C++&amp;rdquo; is crime against programming)
  Being a C library in a C++ World Why C is still being used C is nice but C++ is nicer Implementing a C++ Wrapper for Hyperscan Takeaways    Being a C library in a C++ World This weekend I was looking at a regex library written by intel called hyperscan. I had needed to use a regex library that was performant and easy to use.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Starting With Realtime Data</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/starting-with-realtime-data/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 20:15:01 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/starting-with-realtime-data/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/starting-with-realtime-data/realtime-splash.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Starting With Realtime Data" /&gt;(or why realtime data is elusive in most organizations)
  Data, Data and Data How to break out of the cycle National Rail to the Rescue STOMP Protocol ( which I didn&amp;rsquo;t know was a thing ) Re-learning Java in a pinch Note about the Java solution and how it works On to writing to Kafka What Next?    Data, Data and Data   Drowning in Data but Thirsting for Insights  These days the mantra is always data, data and more data.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Learning In Engineering Organizations</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/learninginorganizations/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 15:36:00 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/learninginorganizations/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osadalakmal.github.io/img/learning-in-orgs.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Learning In Engineering Organizations" /&gt;Learning In Software Engineering Organizations   The Learning Organization: A Lit Review by giulia.forsythe licensed under CC BY 2.0   Learning in Organizations Why Learning Matters for Organizations What is different about engineering organizations How to learn in Big Organizations  Corporate Knowledge Systems. Index, tag and disseminate Automate with APIs Chat your way to knowledge Newsletters and Blogs      Learning in Organizations In almost all organizations that I have been part of since I graduated there have come a time when we had to teach something to the whole team.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Not your grandmas&#39; docker - Part 2</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/container-part2/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 10:00:50 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/container-part2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osadalakmal.github.io/img/container-arial.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Not your grandmas&#39; docker - Part 2" /&gt;Components of the container ecosystem  Container Engines Container Host Registry Server Container Orchestration Container Runtime      Now that we have discussed the basics of containers, lets dive in to the details. Modern container tooling goes way beyond simply running an OS image in a separate context.
Components of the container ecosystem  Container Ecosystem 
Container Engines A container engine will run a container given the user input to do so.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Not your grandmas&#39; docker - Part 1</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/container-intro/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 14:00:50 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/container-intro/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osadalakmal.github.io/img/container-arial.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Not your grandmas&#39; docker - Part 1" /&gt;Operating System Level Virtualization  chroot Solaris Zones and Containers Systemd nspawn LXC/LXD   Enter docker Why not docker? What buildah is    Most of us got introduced to containers with docker. In fact it seems that docker for most intents and purposes and has become synonym with containers. However there is a vast landscape of technology underneath this seemingly simple facade of containers. So lets try and dig in to what a container is before we introduce the tooling that we will be using today.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Adventures in WSL Land</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/wsladventures/wsladventures/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 12:00:05 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/wsladventures/wsladventures/</guid>
        <description>Adventures in WSL Land Recently I have joined a new company and as almost always is the case ( at least in Sri Lanka ) I received a laptopthat runs Windows. In this case it was running a rather old version of Windows 10 that did not support WSL2. This documents my adventures in getting this laptop setup so that I can have a relatively modest working and development environment familiar to most *nix developers.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Cloud9 - A cloud based IDE for your code</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/cloud9/cloud9/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 12:33:51 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/cloud9/cloud9/</guid>
        <description>Cloud9 - A cloud based IDE for your code I first heard of cloud9 before it was acquired by AWS in 2016. In those days it was a novelty. But the good sort - the sort of thing you think of and say &amp;ldquo;Man, if only I had that sort of flexibility&amp;rdquo;. This was before Google docs was a widespread thing and collaborating on a cloud IDE that existed independently of your computer was unheard of.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Codestar - A new way to get started on AWS Projects</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/codestar/codestar/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 20:08:50 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/codestar/codestar/</guid>
        <description>Codestar - A new approach to development on AWS Codestar is a relatively new approach to creating new application that run on AWS infrastructure. The interesting thing about this seems to be that it gives newbie developers like myself to get bootstrapped and go from zero to hundred in a relatively short time period.
 InitialScreen 
This is the initial screen shown when you first try to create a codestar project.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Cost Of Allocation in High Performance Systems</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/allocationcost/allocationcost/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 08:08:50 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/allocationcost/allocationcost/</guid>
        <description>Impact of unproductive work In high performance systems we try to make sure we do as little unproductive work as we possible. As Andrei Alexdrascu points out in one of his presentations on the subject, the fastest bit of code is the code that does not run. So it is essential that we try to avoid as much unproductive work as possible.
When we say unproductive work it usually seems we are talking about unwanted calculations, operations, file access and db access.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>SQLite for High Throughput Applications</title>
        <link>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/sqliteperformance/sqliteperformance/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 15:27:50 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osadalakmal.github.io/posts/sqliteperformance/sqliteperformance/</guid>
        <description>SQLite is an embedded SQL Library. This means that It is a single library that you link against and now your application has access to a full blown SQL server within the process itself. It does not need a separate tool to access the database. The database is a single file stored on Disk. It also comes with a binary that can read and manipulate databases
When to use SQLite The advise straight from its creator is to use it to replace flat files.</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
