<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Communication on Osada Blog – Thoughts on Software Engineering, Programming, Systems, and Life</title>
        <link>https://osada.blog/categories/communication/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Communication on Osada Blog – Thoughts on Software Engineering, Programming, Systems, and Life</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-gb</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 21:50:31 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://osada.blog/categories/communication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>The Shipping Forecast and the Art of Communication</title>
        <link>https://osada.blog/posts/be-more-like-shipping-forecast/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 21:50:31 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osada.blog/posts/be-more-like-shipping-forecast/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osada.blog/posts/be-more-like-shipping-forecast/shipping.webp" alt="Featured image of post The Shipping Forecast and the Art of Communication" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an immigrant to the UK, I had to absorb the culture as a grown-up. Things that others learned through cultural osmosis, I had to consciously seek out and understand - including the norms of UK TV and radio. Now that I&amp;rsquo;m working on BBC Sounds, it&amp;rsquo;s more important than ever for me to be aware of the cultural touchstones of Radioland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I had no idea what the Shipping Forecast was, although it seemed as quintessentially British as it could get. I only knew it from the “Calm” playlists on BBC Sounds - a chant-like recital of odd place names and numbers that people found oddly soothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then one day, exhausted and a little breathless after a hike, I caught the Shipping Forecast live on Radio 4. For the first time, I truly listened. Its rhythm was regular, clipped, steady - strangely calming. Most of it was guessable: numbers for wind force, the last part for visibility. But the place names were a mystery. My curiosity was piqued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What struck me when I dug deeper was how deliberately it was designed - not for poetry, but for survival. A century on air, the Shipping Forecast continues to save sailors’ lives because of the way it communicates: clearly, consistently, and unambiguously in a noisy environment. And that, I realized, is exactly the lesson we need for technical communication in our own teams and organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-crash-course-on-the-shipping-forecast&#34;&gt;A Crash Course on the Shipping Forecast
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Shipping Forecast is a weather bulletin for the seas around the British Isles. Issued by the UK Met Office, it has been on the air since 1924. Its origins trace back to Vice-Admiral Robert FitzRoy in the 1860s, who began issuing storm warnings to reduce shipwrecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;structure-of-the-forecast&#34;&gt;Structure of the Forecast
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Synopsis&lt;/strong&gt; - A summary of pressure systems (highs and lows), their current location, pressure in millibars, and their expected movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: “Low, Rockall, 990, slow-moving, expected 1002 by 0600 tomorrow.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sea Area Forecasts&lt;/strong&gt; - 31 named sea areas around the UK and Ireland, always read in the same order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;each-areas-forecast-includes&#34;&gt;Each Area’s Forecast Includes
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wind direction and strength (Beaufort scale, 0-12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weather (e.g., rain, showers, fog, fair)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visibility (good = &amp;gt;5 miles, moderate = 2-5 miles, poor = 1-2 miles, very poor = &amp;lt;1 mile)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional tidal notes in extended bulletins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-facts&#34;&gt;Key Facts
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First broadcast: 1924 on the BBC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still broadcast four times daily on Radio 4 (0048, 0520, 1201, 1754).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It covers 31 sea areas, such as Viking, Dogger, German Bight, Fastnet, and Rockall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The language is deliberately short, standardized, and unambiguous for clarity on poor radios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-the-seas-are-rough-organizational-communication&#34;&gt;When the Seas Are Rough: Organizational Communication
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve experienced firsthand how crucial communication becomes during upheaval. When an organization goes through a major transformation, communication is not an afterthought-it&amp;rsquo;s the glue that holds everything together. As leaders, how we handle this communication is paramount, because the success of the transformation depends on it. The people we manage look to us to provide information and reassurance that the disruptions and changes are truly for the good of the organization. They want to know how it will impact them, and what tomorrow will look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, too often, communication during transformations feels overbearing. Updates are packed with details people don’t need or aren’t equipped to decipher. The essentials get buried, and people tune out. In tuning out, they miss the pieces of information that could genuinely help them navigate change. Even more harmful, they may interpret a lack of clarity and superfluous details as an intentional effort to obfuscate. This quickly erodes trust, making it harder to get positive buy-in for the changes we are implementing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has always frustrated me. We need a framework that keeps communicators focused on what matters most - the salient details, presented consistently, with no ambiguity. And the Shipping Forecast offers exactly that model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-noisy-inefficient-communication&#34;&gt;The Problem: Noisy, Inefficient Communication
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the situations that matter most - organizational updates, incident response, migrations - the goal is simple: provide enough information to give employees the confidence they need. But communication often fails in predictable ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updates ramble and lose people’s attention. For example, an incident update that drags on for ten minutes without ever stating the impact or action items leaves everyone confused.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Messages lack structure, so if you join late, you’re lost. A migration briefing that jumps between topics with no clear beginning, middle, or end forces people to guess where they are in the plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jargon creeps in, introducing ambiguity. Saying “we’ll refactor the orchestration layer” without explaining what systems that refers to leaves many stakeholders unsure of the change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some things are over-explained while others are skipped. A design review might go into detail about which framework version is used but never mention who owns the rollout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updates arrive inconsistently, so no one knows when to expect them. A status email sent at random times each week is quickly ignored because the team cannot rely on it as a dependable source of truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is confusion, frustration, and wasted energy. In moments of transformation or crisis, the cost is even higher: teams feel unmoored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-the-shipping-forecast-gets-right&#34;&gt;What the Shipping Forecast Gets Right
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Shipping Forecast has perfected communication for noisy, high-stakes environments. Its principles are deceptively simple but powerful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consistency&lt;/strong&gt;: Always in the same order, with the same structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brevity&lt;/strong&gt;: Nothing is superfluous; only the essentials remain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarity&lt;/strong&gt;: Standardized words ensure there is no ambiguity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coverage&lt;/strong&gt;: The whole coastline is covered, end to end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reliability&lt;/strong&gt;: Delivered four times daily, without fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repetition&lt;/strong&gt;: Core facts are repeated until they stick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For sailors, these principles are life-saving. For us, they can make the difference between communication that enables action and communication that creates noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-consistency-coverage-and-reliability-matter&#34;&gt;Why Consistency, Coverage and Reliability Matter
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In organizational transformations, consistency and reliable repetition aren’t dull-they build confidence. People are dealing with new ways of working, new technology, and new structures. In that environment, clear consistent repetition is reassurance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It shows nothing is being hidden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It signals that everything has been thoroughly thought through.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It makes the audience confident in the plan because they can see its completeness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For engineering managers and tech leads, this matters directly. Your team should come to believe that communication is crafted for their benefit, that it was intentional and thoughtful, and that leadership cares about making the change succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-make-your-communication-more-like-the-forecast&#34;&gt;How to Make Your Communication More Like the Forecast
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When clarity matters most - for organizational updates, technical changes, incidents, or migrations - we should borrow from the Shipping Forecast:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;consistency&#34;&gt;Consistency
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use the same structure every time. For example, always start incident updates with impact, then mitigation, then next steps. Likewise, if you write weekly status reports, keep the same headings so readers know where to look for information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;brevity&#34;&gt;Brevity
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cut the noise; provide only what matters. An update that simply says, “Service X is degraded, engineers are working on rollback, ETA 20 minutes” is far more effective than three paragraphs of background detail. A migration notice that summarizes the change in three bullet points is more likely to be read than a three-page essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;clarity&#34;&gt;Clarity
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avoid ambiguity; use the simplest words. Instead of saying “there are issues with authentication subsystems,” say “users cannot log in.” Instead of “orchestration layer refactor,” say “we are changing how services talk to each other.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;coverage&#34;&gt;Coverage
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cover the topic end to end. If you announce a new deployment pipeline, don’t just describe the technical flow; also mention who owns it, how teams onboard, and what support is available. Similarly, if you communicate a process change, spell out both what is changing and what stays the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reliability&#34;&gt;Reliability
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deliver updates at a predictable rhythm. Sending a daily stand-up note at 9am sharp builds trust. Publishing a weekly engineering summary every Friday ensures people rely on it. Irregular communication erodes confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;repetition&#34;&gt;Repetition
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reinforce the essentials until they stick. In a transformation, it is worth saying three times: “The old system will be retired on 31 October.” In incident communications, repeat the key action: “Restart your client if you see this error.” Repetition of core facts reassures people that they haven’t missed something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;closing&#34;&gt;Closing
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a century, the Shipping Forecast has guided sailors through storms. I discovered it by chance and was struck by how soothing it was. But the reason it’s soothing is the same reason it’s effective: it is structured, consistent, reliable, and repetitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not every kind of communication should be like the Shipping Forecast - some moments demand storytelling, persuasion, or brainstorming. But when the goal is to disseminate information clearly and efficiently, especially in noisy or turbulent environments, the lesson holds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good communication doesn’t just inform. Like the Shipping Forecast, it enables people to act with confidence, no matter how stormy the seas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Nemawashi - Power of building consensus</title>
        <link>https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 18:36:00 +0530</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/nemawashi-main.webp" alt="Featured image of post Nemawashi - Power of building consensus" /&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;nemawashi---power-of-building-consensus&#34;&gt;Nemawashi - Power of building consensus
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the fast-paced world of business and decision-making, ensuring that everyone is on the same page and in agreement is essential. A crucial aspect of effective decision-making is building consensus before a meeting takes place. Consensus-building allows teams to align their thoughts, opinions, and goals, leading to more productive meetings and better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Japanese culture, there is a term that encapsulates this process beautifully - &amp;ldquo;nemawashi.&amp;rdquo; Nemawashi refers to the practice of laying the groundwork and seeking agreement among stakeholders before a meeting or decision-making process begins. It is a fundamental concept that plays a significant role in achieving harmony and collaboration within organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, we will delve into the concept of nemawashi and explore its practical implications for building consensus before meetings. We will discuss the cultural significance of nemawashi in Japan and its relevance in a broader context. Furthermore, we will outline effective strategies that can help you incorporate nemawashi techniques to foster collaboration, engagement, and successful decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we try to understand the art of building consensus and discover how nemawashi can transform your meetings into more fruitful and harmonious experiences. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore the power of nemawashi and its impact on achieving alignment within your team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;understanding-nemawashi&#34;&gt;Understanding Nemawashi
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nemawashi, rooted in Japanese culture, holds valuable lessons for building consensus before meetings. By embracing this practice, teams can set the stage for productive discussions and decision-making. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore the meaning and significance of nemawashi, along with some practical examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, nemawashi involves laying the groundwork and seeking agreement among stakeholders before a meeting or decision-making process begins. This process allows individuals to voice their opinions, address concerns, and find common ground, leading to smoother decision-making and improved outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-1-toyotas-decision-making-process&#34;&gt;Example 1: Toyota&amp;rsquo;s Decision-Making Process
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the most famous examples of nemawashi can be found in the decision-making process at Toyota, a renowned Japanese automobile manufacturer. Before any major decision is made, Toyota follows a meticulous approach that involves extensive consultation and consensus-building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams engage in cross-functional meetings, where representatives from various departments share their perspectives, concerns, and ideas. This process allows for a comprehensive understanding of the issue at hand and helps identify potential obstacles or risks. By incorporating nemawashi, Toyota ensures that decisions are made collaboratively, taking into account the viewpoints of all relevant stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/Nemawashi-japanese-chars.webp&#34;
	width=&#34;1552&#34;
	height=&#34;1331&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/Nemawashi-japanese-chars_hu_b4ecb7127663ecfa.webp 480w, https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/Nemawashi-japanese-chars_hu_2c0ae54b49fcee5a.webp 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;116&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;279px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Sidebar: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2011/01/how-toyota-makes-decisions&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Read more about Toyota&amp;rsquo;s decision-making process here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-2-us-government-and-legislative-process&#34;&gt;Example 2: U.S. Government and Legislative Process
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;While nemawashi is rooted in Japanese culture, similar principles of consensus-building can be observed in the U.S. government&amp;rsquo;s legislative process. Before bills are brought to the floor for a vote, extensive negotiations, discussions, and consensus-building efforts take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the U.S. Congress, lawmakers engage in committee meetings, hearings, and informal conversations to gather input from various stakeholders. This process allows representatives to address concerns, incorporate amendments, and build consensus among different factions. Through these deliberations, consensus is sought to increase the chances of a bill&amp;rsquo;s successful passage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of how the U.S. legislative process and consensus-building are depicted is the television show &amp;ldquo;The West Wing.&amp;rdquo; The show portrays the inner workings of the White House and provides insights into the intricate process of developing and passing legislation. It showcases the efforts of policymakers to build consensus, negotiate, and seek agreement among different parties to advance their policy agendas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &amp;ldquo;The West Wing&amp;rdquo; is a fictional representation, it offers viewers a glimpse into the complexities and nuances of consensus-building in the U.S. political landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/the-west-wing-discussion.webp&#34;
	width=&#34;2000&#34;
	height=&#34;1333&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/the-west-wing-discussion_hu_88b234675f94369d.webp 480w, https://osada.blog/posts/nemawashi-power-of-consensus/the-west-wing-discussion_hu_b5c97dca5b65ed9f.webp 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;150&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;360px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Sidebar : &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/2019/12/20/790948548/the-west-wing-podcast-a-reminder-of-when-consensus-seemed-possible&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Explore more about &amp;ldquo;The West Wing&amp;rdquo; and its depiction of the U.S. legislative process here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By highlighting this example, we can observe that nemawashi-inspired practices and consensus-building efforts exist beyond cultural boundaries. Consensus-building is a universal concept that plays a crucial role in effective decision-making across diverse settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;strategies-for-building-consensus&#34;&gt;Strategies for Building Consensus
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building consensus before a meeting requires careful planning, effective communication, and fostering a collaborative environment. By employing the following strategies, you can create a foundation for productive discussions and decision-making:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preparing for the Meeting - Thorough preparation is essential for successful consensus-building. Consider the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gather Information: Seek input from stakeholders and team members before the meeting. Collect diverse perspectives and insights to gain a comprehensive understanding of the topic at hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Address Concerns: Take the time to identify and address any potential concerns or objections that participants may have. Addressing these early on can help mitigate resistance and pave the way for consensus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One-on-One Meetings: Engage in individual discussions with key stakeholders to understand their viewpoints and gather feedback. This personal touch allows for open and honest conversations, fostering a sense of inclusion and trust.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invite Contributions: Show respect for stakeholders by genuinely considering their perspectives and inviting their contributions. Recognize that they may bring valuable insights and solutions to the table. This approach promotes collaboration and a sense of ownership among participants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective Communication Techniques - Clear and open communication is vital for building consensus. Consider these techniques:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active Listening: Practice attentive and empathetic listening. Encourage participants to express their thoughts, concerns, and ideas, and ensure that everyone feels heard and respected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitate Constructive Discussions: Create an inclusive environment where diverse perspectives are encouraged. Set ground rules for respectful dialogue and constructive debate. Guide the conversation towards finding common ground and shared goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual Aids and Examples: Utilize visual aids, data, and real-life examples to illustrate your points and foster a shared understanding. Visual representations can bridge gaps in perception and facilitate consensus-building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building Trust and Collaboration - Trust and collaboration are key elements of consensus-building. Consider the following approaches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage Collaboration: Foster a culture of collaboration by promoting teamwork and emphasizing collective goals. Encourage participants to work together, share ideas, and find mutually beneficial solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparency and Accountability: Promote transparency in decision-making processes. Clearly communicate the rationale behind decisions and ensure accountability for actions. This builds trust and confidence among team members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inclusive Decision-Making: Involve all relevant stakeholders in the decision-making process. Seek diverse perspectives and involve those who may be affected by the outcome. This inclusive approach increases ownership and commitment to the decisions made.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By incorporating these strategies into your consensus-building efforts, you can lay a solid foundation for successful meetings. Remember to appear open to problem discussions rather than solely focusing on solutions and demonstrate respect for stakeholders by inviting their contributions. Consensus-building requires active engagement and continuous effort to create an environment where diverse voices are valued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up we should discuss the effective ways of communication in order to execute above strategies. And discuss why trust is pramount to executing these strategies. Expect that in the next installment of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
